Guide to the Santerre collection of Charles X, 1535-1855.
Santerre collection of Charles X,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Santerre collection of Charles X, 1535-1855 (bulk 1773-1830)
4603
Charles Charle, 1757-1836.
10.2 linear ft.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Business correspondence, accounts, statements, receipts, vouchers, deeds, transcripts of transactions, and notes, mainly written or collected by the personal or family treasurers of the Comte d'Artois (including his reign as King Charles X) and of his grandson, the count of Chambord and duke of Bordeaux. The collection documents the management of the Comte d'Artois's personal and household finances from 1773 until his permanent exile following the July Revolution of 1830, with documents concerning some family estates extending back to 1535. It also documents the management of the Comte de Chambord's personal and household finances through 1855. Most items are from the pre-Revolutionary period (1773-1789), the Restoration (1814-1830), or items concerning the Comte de Chambord (from 1828-1855), including expenses for his education and begging letters received by him or his tutors. Materials from Restoration period include a complete set of annual accounts of the Comte d'Artois's household from 1815-1830.
Treasurers of the Comte d'Artois or of his family were: Barthélémy Pierre Droüet de Santerre, Anselme Barthélémy Droüet de Santerre, and Henri Louis de Belleville. Correspondents include them and Baron Ange-Hyacinthe Maxence de Damas (tutor of the Comte de Chambord), Abbé Tharin (Chambord's preceptor), and the Marquis Amédée-David de Pastoret (administrator of Chambord's possessions after 1840).
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Count of Artois; King of France 1824-1830.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Business correspondence, accounts, statements, receipts, vouchers, deeds, transcripts of transactions, and notes, mainly written or collected by the personal or family treasurers of the Comte d'Artois (including his reign as King Charles X) and of his grandson, the count of Chambord and duke of Bordeaux. The collection documents the management of the Comte d'Artois's personal and household finances from 1773 until his permanent exile following the July Revolution of 1830, with documents concerning some family estates extending back to 1535. It also documents the management of the Comte de Chambord's personal and household finances through 1855. Most items are from the pre-Revolutionary period (1773-1789), the Restoration (1814-1830), or items concerning the Comte de Chambord (from 1828-1855), including expenses for his education and begging letters received by him or his tutors. Materials from Restoration period include a complete set of annual accounts of the Comte d'Artois's household from 1815-1830.
Treasurers of the Comte d'Artois or of his family were: Barthélémy Pierre Droüet de Santerre, Anselme Barthélémy Droüet de Santerre, and Henri Louis de Belleville. Correspondents include them and Baron Ange-Hyacinthe Maxence de Damas (tutor of the Comte de Chambord), Abbé Tharin (Chambord's preceptor), and the Marquis Amédée-David de Pastoret (administrator of Chambord's possessions after 1840).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Charles King of France, 1757-1836.; Charles King of France, 1757-1836.; Chambord, Henri-Charles-Ferdinand-Marie-Dieudonné d'Artois, comte de, 1820-1883.; Chambord, Henri-Charles-Ferdinand-Marie-Dieudonné d'Artois, comte de, 1820-1883; Charles King of France, 1757-1836; Santerre, Barthélémy Pierre Droüet de, 1734-1818.; Santerre, Anselme Barthélémy Droüet de.; Belleville, Henri Louis de.; Damas, Ange-Hyacinthe-Maxence, baron de, 1785-1862.; Tharin, abbé.; Pastoret, Amédée-David, marquis de, 1791-1851.
Subjects:
Land tenure -- History. -- France; Land titles -- History. -- France; Administration of estates -- History. -- France; Finance, Personal -- History. -- France; Education -- History. -- France; Upper classes -- Education -- France.; Domestic relations -- France.; Administration of estates; Domestic relations; Economic history; Education; Finance, Personal; Land tenure; Land titles -- Registration and transfer
Places:
France -- Sources. -- Charles X, 1824-1830; France -- Sources. -- Louis XVI, 1774-1793; France -- Sources. -- Restoration, 1814-1830; France -- Economic conditions -- 18th century.; France -- Economic conditions -- 19th century.; France
Form and Genre Terms:
History; Sources
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Charles X Materials
  - A-Bor (Box 1)
  - Bordeaux, Henri, duc de A - N (Box 2)
  - Bordeaux, Henri, duc de O - Z (Box 3)
  - Bos - Charles X Archives (Box 4)
  - Charles X Domaines A - Deeds 1669 (Box 5)
  - Charles X Domaines Deeds 1670 - Obr (Box 6)
  - Charles X Domaines Obs - Z (Box 7)
  - Charles X Maison - Tresor. Compte (Box 8)
  - Tresor. Compte de l'Exercise 1776 - 1826 (Box 9)
  - Tresor. Compte de l'Exercise 1827 - D (Box 10)
  - Charles X Ea - Ew (Box 11)
  - Charles X Ex - N (Box 12)
  - O - Rem (Box 13)
  - Ren - Cz (Box 14)
  - Daa - Daz (Box 15)
  - Dea - Der (Box 16)
  - Des - France.A (Box 17)
  - France.B (Box 18)
  - France.C - J (Box 19)
  - K - Lemerle, A (December 1848) (Box 20)
  - Lemerle, A January 1849 - February 1852 (Box 21)
  - Lemerle, A March 1852 - N (Box 22)
  - O - Santerre (Box 23)
  - Santerre, Anselme (Box 24)
  - Santerre, Anselme - Sz (Box 25)
  - T - Z (Box 26)